<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<textbook>
<chap_52_67>
<!--    includes markup of chapters 52-67 (olga)-->
     
     
      <start><chap>52. The Overthrow of Tsarism in February 1917.
     
     Uprising in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>. Tsar <person>Nicholas II</person> and his ministers were at a loss as to how to cope with the defeat at the front and the impending revolution. They were at a loss for what to do. Even the bourgeois "Cadet" party and its leader, <person>Miliukov</person>, ceased supporting the Tsar due to defeats at the front; but the Cadets also feared revolution. The bourgeoisie decided to remove <person>Nicholas II</person> from power and install his brother Mikhail on the throne, suppress the nascent revolutionary movement, and continue the war.
      Those close to the Tsar advised <person>Nicholas II</person> to end the war, conclude a separate peace with the Germans, and then deal with the revolution.
      The plans of the Tsar and the bourgeoisie did not come to fruition. They were forestalled by an uprising of workers and soldiers, which began in February 1917.
      In early 1917, the starving and war-weary workers of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> went on strike. The <people>Bolsheviks</people> led the workers' struggle. They also infiltrated soldiers' barracks, calling on the army to support the workers in their fight against the Tsar. Working men and women took to the streets and demanded:
      "Down with the war!" Down with the tsarist government! Bread! Peace!
      Soon the workers began to understand that the tsarist government could not be defeated by a single strike; an armed uprising was necessary—and they rebelled.
      The tsarist ministers gave the order to shoot the workers without mercy. In the city center, police set up machine guns on rooftops and in attics and fired at the demonstrators.
      The heroic struggle of the <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> workers also drew soldiers into the revolution.
      On February 27, the troops in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> refused to fire on the workers and began to go over to the side of the people.
      The rebellious workers and soldiers arrested the tsarist ministers and imprisoned them. Imprisoned revolutionaries were released from prison. Crowds burned police and courthouses. Young workers and working women participated in the uprising alongside their brothers and husbands.
      Tsar <person>Nicholas II</person>, who was outside <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> at the time, sent troops from the front against the rebellious people. But revolutionary workers and soldiers rode out to meet them, explained what they were fighting for, and convinced the troops to disobey the orders of the tsar and the generals. The soldiers obeyed the workers. The revolution triumphed over the tsarist regime.
      When news of the revolution's victory in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> reached other cities and the front, workers and soldiers overthrew the tsarist regime locally as well.
      Following the example of the first revolution of 1905, Soviets were created everywhere, but these were no longer just Soviets of workers' deputies, but Soviets of workers' and soldiers' deputies. This marked the difference between the February Revolution of 1917 and the revolution of 1905. The soldiers' deputies in the Soviets were, in essence, peasant deputies, disguised in soldiers' uniforms for the occasion. This meant that the Soviets of workers' and soldiers' deputies were, in fact, Soviets of workers' and peasants' deputies. This meant that an alliance of workers and peasants against the tsarist regime had already formed, and the Soviets of workers' and soldiers' deputies became the organs of this alliance.
      Without this alliance, the people could not have overthrown the tsar, and the revolution could not have triumphed.
      Two powers. The bourgeoisie managed to exploit the petty-bourgeois politicians, the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries, who constituted the majority in the Soviets, and with their help seized power in the country. Traitors to the revolution—the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries—enabled the bourgeoisie to establish their own bourgeois Provisional Government.
      But the Soviets continued to exist alongside the Provisional Government. Two powers emerged in the country.
     
      Upon arriving in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> on April 3, 1917, the leader of the proletariat, V. I. <person >Lenin</person>, was greeted by revolutionary sailors and soldiers.
     
      The bourgeoisie and the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries entrenched in the Soviets sought to continue the war with Germany to a victorious end. The land remained in the hands of the landowners. Capitalists continued to rob the workers. The oppression of the peoples of Russia remained.
      <person >Lenin</person>, in letters from abroad, and the <people>Bolsheviks</people>, led by Comrade Stalin, who had returned from exile, denounced the Provisional Government to the people and exposed the deceptions of the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries.
      On April 3, 1917, <person >Lenin</person> returned to Russia with great difficulty from abroad. All of revolutionary <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>—workers, sailors, and soldiers—gathered to greet him. The cheers for <person >Lenin</person> were endless. <person >Lenin</person> climbed onto an armored car, spoke to the people, and into the hushed crowd he issued a fiery appeal: "Long live the world socialist revolution!" It was a call to fight against the bourgeois Provisional Government, to establish working-class power, and to fight for socialism.
     
      XII. The Great October Socialist Revolution in Russia
     
      </chap>
    <chap> 53. The <people>Bolsheviks</people> Prepare the Socialist Revolution
     
      . The masses follow the <people>Bolsheviks</people>. Upon <person >Lenin</person>'s arrival, the party convened a conference of <people>Bolsheviks</people>. Delegates representing 80,000 party members from all over Russia converged on <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>. Molotov, Voroshilov, Sverdlov, Kuibyshev, Dzerzhinsky, and many others attended the conference. <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin presided over the conference. They pointed out that the working class had accomplished only its first task—the abolition of the tsarist autocracy in Russia. They said a second task still needed to be accomplished—the socialist revolution. They said the party still faced a serious and arduous struggle, because the bourgeoisie, which had come to dominate the country, would not relinquish power without fierce resistance.
      They called on the party to win a majority in the Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies, as well as in the Soviets of Peasants' Deputies, and to expel the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries from them.
      <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin called on the <people>Bolsheviks</people> to organize the masses to fight for the socialist revolution. For the socialist revolution to succeed, they argued, the working class, in close alliance with the poor peasantry, must overthrow the rule of the bourgeoisie. It was necessary to curb the bourgeoisie, wrest the land from the landowners and give it to the peasants for use, grant freedom to the oppressed peoples of Russia, and immediately end the war.
     
      The peasants demanded land. A fellow sailor called for the immediate, organized seizure of the landowners' lands.
     
      <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin's proposals were accepted by the conference. The <people>Bolsheviks</people> launched a massive campaign among the workers, soldiers, and sailors. They also launched a campaign among the peasants. They explained the conference's decisions and called on the people to fight against the Provisional Government for the establishment of Soviet power, an end to the war, and the immediate transfer of all land to the peasants.
      Workers' and soldiers' demonstrations began in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>. In April, a demonstration of workers and soldiers was organized. The demonstrators carried placards and banners with Bolshevik slogans:
      "Down with the war!
      " "Down with the capitalist ministers!
      " "All power to the Soviets!"
      The Provisional Government, together with the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries, was forced to remove the most hated capitalist ministers, Guchkov and Milyukov, from their posts and included several <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries in its ranks.
      But the government's policies remained unchanged. The war continued, landowners controlled the land, oppressed peoples remained disenfranchised, and workers were threatened with lockouts (the closure of enterprises).
      The revolutionary mood of the masses grew. They increasingly listened to the voice of the <people>Bolsheviks</people>. The Bolshevik Party grew stronger.
      In early June 1917, the First All-Russian Congress of Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies was held in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>.
      At this congress, the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries still held a majority. They secured the congress's approval for support of the bourgeois government and an offensive at the front.
      The offensive at the front began then. It ended in defeat for the Russian army. The soldiers were reluctant to go into battle, refusing to fight for the interests of the bourgeoisie and demanding the transfer of all power to the Soviets. In vain did the Provisional Government's Minister of War, the Socialist Revolutionary Kerensky, try to persuade the soldiers to shed their blood for a cause alien to them. "The bourgeoisie needs the war," the soldiers replied, "let them fight themselves." The Provisional Government ordered the execution of soldiers who refused to go into battle.
      The soldiers became increasingly convinced of the betrayal of their interests by the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries and defected to the <people>Bolsheviks</people>. Demonstrations of workers and soldiers began again in Russia's major cities.
      The July demonstration and the mutiny of General Kornilov. The summer of 1917 arrived. The Provisional Government still had not satisfied a single demand of the workers, soldiers, peasants, and oppressed peoples of Russia.
      The devastation in industry and on the railways intensified. Factories and plants were shut down, there were no raw materials or fuel. There was a shortage of bread and meat. Famine was looming.
      The workers' struggle against the capitalists and their government intensified. Strikes were continuous. Workers organized their own armed units—the Red Guard. Peasant uprisings broke out in the villages.
      Soldiers left the front in the thousands. Oppressed peoples, denied liberation by the Provisional Government, came forward with their just demands.
      On July 3, 1917, masses of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> workers, soldiers, and sailors demonstrated under Bolshevik slogans. The bourgeoisie, in collusion with the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries, called in elite cadet and kulak military units from the front and executed the demonstration, smashing workers' organizations.
     
      Shooting of the demonstration on July 3, 1917, in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>.
     
      Cadets and officers attacked the editorial office of the newspaper Pravda. <people>Bolsheviks</people> were arrested and imprisoned. The <people>Bolsheviks</people> were forced to go underground again. The Provisional Government ordered <person >Lenin</person>'s arrest. At the insistence of the Party, <person >Lenin</person> went into hiding. <person >Lenin</person> disguised himself as a worker and, with a passport in the name of a worker named Ivanov, lived in a hut on the outskirts of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>, near Sestroretsk, and some time later moved to Finland. Bourgeois bloodhounds hunted <person >Lenin</person> in vain. The workers protected their beloved leader by all means.
      The bourgeoisie raged in the rear and at the front. Even the most backward workers began to understand the consequences of the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries, who defended the interests of the bourgeoisie. More and more workers joined the ranks of the <people>Bolsheviks</people>. The membership of the Bolshevik Party increased to 200,000.
      At the end of July, the Sixth Congress of the Bolshevik Party convened in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>.
      <person >Lenin</person> was not present at the congress. He was in hiding. Stalin led the congress. He called on the party to prepare for an armed uprising.
      The congress outlined the path to victory for the socialist revolution and developed measures to combat the economic devastation in the country.
      Delegates scattered across Russia began preparing workers and poor peasants for an uprising against the Provisional Government, to overthrow its authority, and to establish the power of the Soviets, the power of workers and peasants.
      Then the bourgeoisie and landowners organized a conspiracy against the revolution. On their instructions, General Kornilov assembled large detachments of officers, Cossacks, and backward troops and marched them on <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> to smash the Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies, strangle the workers and peasants, and declare himself the absolute ruler of Russia.
      At the call of the <people>Bolsheviks</people>, the workers of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> and the <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> troops rose up. Revolutionary agitators—workers and soldiers—sent to meet Kornilov's troops told Kornilov's soldiers of their general's true intentions. The soldiers of Kornilov's regiments refused to oppose the revolution. The bourgeoisie's conspiracy failed. Under pressure from the workers and peasants, Kerensky was forced to arrest Kornilov and imprison him.
      The workers' and soldiers' victory over Kornilov further strengthened the Bolshevik Party's influence.
      After the Kornilov rebellion, workers and soldiers began expelling the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries from the Soviets and electing <people>Bolsheviks</people> in their place. In the fall of 1917, the majority of the <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> and <place = type "city">Moscow</place> Soviets went over to the <people>Bolsheviks</people>. The Soviets became the true centers of the proletarian revolution. They armed the workers, created the Red Guard, and prepared for an armed uprising.
      In early October, <person >Lenin</person>, hiding from the bourgeois government, appeared in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> to lead the uprising. <person >Lenin</person> declared that the workers' victory was now assured, that an armed uprising must be launched immediately, the government of the bourgeoisie, the <people>Mensheviks</people>, and the Socialist Revolutionaries must be overthrown, and the power of the Soviets must be established.
     
    </chap><chap>54. The socialist revolution triumphed.
     
      The victorious uprising of October 25 (November 7), 1917. The Bolshevik Party was preparing for the final, decisive battle—the overthrow of bourgeois power by force of arms.
      The moment for the uprising was well chosen. The world war continued. In Russia, the majority of workers followed the <people>Bolsheviks</people>. The compromising Menshevik and Socialist-Revolutionary parties had lost the trust of the working people. Many Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies were in Bolshevik hands. The workers had their own strong trade unions and the Red Guard. The peasants did not want to wait for the convocation of the Constituent Assembly, as the compromising Socialist-Revolutionary and Menshevik parties advised them to do, and followed the <people>Bolsheviks</people>, who demanded the immediate seizure of the landowners' lands. They expelled the landowners from their namedays and seized the land. The soldiers did not want to continue the war. They rejected Kerensky's order to fight to the bitter end and demanded peace. Not only Russian workers and peasants, but also the peoples of Transcaucasia, Ukraine, Belarus, Central Asia, and Finland rose up against Kerensky's Provisional Government. The <people>Bolsheviks</people> vigorously prepared for the uprising. Its plan was carefully developed.
     
      V. I. <person >Lenin</person> (1870–1924)
     
      <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin among the Red Guards.
     
      But in the most decisive days of preparation for the uprising, Kamenev, Zinoviev, and Trotsky betrayed the plans and dates of the uprising to the bourgeoisie. The Provisional Government, having learned of the uprising from traitors, urgently mobilized troops loyal to it to fight it. But the days of bourgeois rule were numbered. The Central Committee of the Bolshevik Party created a combat center to lead the uprising, headed by Comrade Stalin. Following <person >Lenin</person>'s instructions, on October 24, 1917, the combat center launched the uprising. <person >Lenin</person> stood at its head.
     
      V. I. <person >Lenin</person> leads the uprising in the October days of 1917.
     
      As one, the Red Guards, revolutionary soldiers, and sailors of Kronstadt rose up in response to the call of the Bolshevik Party. The courage, revolutionary drive, and discipline of the revolutionary soldiers quickly did their job. All government institutions and military posts in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> were occupied by the Red Guards. The ministers of the Provisional Government, along with detachments of officers and cadets, fortified themselves in the Winter Palace. On October 25, revolutionary troops surrounded the palace. The revolutionary cruiser Aurora and three destroyers entered the Neva River. The siege of the palace lasted until evening. Darkness fell. Only the enormous Winter Palace remained illuminated. Toward nightfall, the fighting intensified. Machine guns rattled. Rifle volleys rang out. A firefight broke out between the troops entrenched in the palace and the advancing revolutionaries. The Red Guards began their assault on the palace.
     
      Revolutionary sailors storm the Winter Palace in October 1917.
     
      The <people>Bolsheviks</people>, who had led the capture of the Winter Palace, offered the besieged forces the opportunity to surrender. They refused. The signal was given. The cannons of the Peter and Paul Fortress opened fire on the Winter Palace. The guns of the cruiser Aurora roared. The artillery fire had its effect. The machine guns in the palace fell silent. The revolutionary troops stormed the palace. The officers and cadets continued to fire back, but soon they surrendered. The Red Guards entered the palace's circular room through a narrow corridor. Several frightened people sat at tables. This was the last bourgeois government in Russia. Kerensky was not there, having managed to escape and hide.
      In the name of the revolution, all the ministers were declared under arrest. Those arrested were taken to the fortress.
      The proletarian revolution had triumphed throughout the country. The working class celebrated its victory. On October 25, the people of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> read <person >Lenin</person>'s proclamation with profound emotion. It declared that the Provisional Government had fallen, and power had passed into the hands of the Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies. The cause for which the people had fought—ending the war, abolishing landlord ownership of land, and establishing a Soviet government—was assured.
      It was now possible to establish workers' control over factories and plants to combat economic devastation.
      The Second All-Russian Congress of Soviets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies opened at the same time. <person >Lenin</person> submitted, and the congress approved, the first three decrees of the Great Proletarian Revolution: on peace, on land, and on power.
      The Decree on Peace proposed that all belligerent states immediately begin negotiations to end the war and conclude a peace on the basis of equality.
      The Decree on Land abolished the landlord class, abolished private landownership, and transferred it to the use of all working people. Peasants received over 150 million hectares of land from the Soviet government.
      The Decree on Power transferred all power in the country to the Soviets.
      Our country became a Soviet Republic.
      The Congress elected the All-Russian Central Executive Committee and the Council of People's Commissars. V. I. <person >Lenin</person> became the head of the Council of People's Commissars. Comrade Stalin was elected People's Commissar for Nationalities.
      Soon after the Congress, Comrade Sverdlov was elected Chairman of the All-Russian Central Executive Committee.
      News of the proletariat's victory in <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> quickly spread throughout the country. In a number of cities, workers had to wage fierce battles to seize power.
     
        <person>Yakov Mikhailovich Sverdlov (1885–1919).</person>
     
      In <place = type "city">Moscow</place>, officers and cadets seized the Kremlin and a number of large buildings. Red Guard workers were forced to dig trenches and wage a real war against counterrevolutionaries. Fighting raged in <place = type "city">Moscow</place> for a whole week. Only with cannon fire did the workers and soldiers force the officers and cadets to surrender.
      Telegrams about the transfer of power to the Soviets flew from all Russian cities to <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>. The peoples of Siberia, Central Asia, Belarus, the Volga region, and the left bank of Ukraine, with the help of the Soviet government, were liberating themselves from centuries-old oppression by the bourgeoisie and landowners.
     
      The capture of the Kremlin by insurgent workers in <place = type "city">Moscow</place> in the October days of 1917.
     
      The victory of the socialist Soviet revolution is thus explained by the following reasons:
      1) The bourgeois government of the Socialist Revolutionary Kerensky had completely failed in the eyes of the workers and peasants. Kerensky sought to continue the war to a victorious conclusion, while the workers, peasants, and soldiers demanded an end to the war and the conclusion of peace. Kerensky sought to preserve the lands for the landowners, while the workers and peasants demanded the immediate seizure of the landowners' lands for the peasants. Kerensky sought to curb the workers, while the workers and peasants demanded the curbing of factory owners and the establishment of workers' organizations over them.
      2) The second reason is that, on the basis of these demands, a strong alliance of workers and peasants was formed and consolidated in the form of the Sonnets of Workers' and Soldiers' Deputies against the bourgeois Provisional Government and its lackeys—the Socialist Revolutionaries and <people>Mensheviks</people>—in support of the Bolshevik Party.
      3) The third reason is that the workers and peasants en masse abandoned the compromising Socialist Revolutionaries and <people>Mensheviks</people> and rallied around the Bolshevik Party, recognizing it as their leader and guide.
      Without these reasons, the October Revolution could not have succeeded.
      The Bolshevik Party organized the Soviet state. From the very first days of the victory of the Great Proletarian Revolution, <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin began organizing the Soviet state as a fraternal socialist union of all peoples. The peoples of Russia received from Soviet power complete liberation, such as no other people in the world had ever experienced.
     
        <person>Felix Edmundovich Dzerzhinsky </person>(1877–1926).
     
      Following the decrees on peace and land, a decree on workers' control was issued. Workers' control was established over capitalists in factories and plants, over the production, storage, purchase, and sale of all food products and raw materials.
      The Council of People's Commissars declared a refusal to pay all debts to foreign states.
      However, defeated in the capital and the country's centers, the enemies of Soviet power—landowners, capitalists, generals, and priests, along with the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries—fled to the outskirts of Russia.
      In the Don region, in right-bank Ukraine, in the Caucasus, in the Orenburg steppes, and in Siberia, they attempted to consolidate their position and organize a campaign against Soviet power. But their own forces were weak, and the workers and peasants did not follow them. The rebellions and conspiracies staged by the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries failed. The Red Guard and the All-Russian Extraordinary Commission for Combating Counter-Revolution (VChK), headed by F. E. Dzerzhinsky, were sufficient to suppress these plots by the Socialist Revolutionaries, <people>Mensheviks</people>, and their Cadets allies.
      The Soviet government's fight against counterrevolutionary conspiracies later became much more difficult when the Cadet and Socialist Revolutionary-Menshevik rebels began to receive direct military support from capitalist states. This constituted a military intervention by capitalist states against Soviet power and the Soviet system. The Soviets' struggle against this intervention lasted for three full years.
     
      XIII. Military intervention. Civil war
     
    </chap><chap>55. The Soviets' struggle for peace. The Germans' seizure of Ukraine.
     
      Peace with Germany. Although the war continued, the old Russian army was no longer capable of fighting, and soldiers fled to their homes. Soldiers returned home on the roofs of train cars, on the buffers and brakes of trains. Exhausted by the war, the country and the army needed a respite. The Council of People's Commissars, based on a decree adopted at the Second Congress of Soviets, appealed to all belligerent powers with a proposal to conclude a general peace. The governments of England and France, then joined by the United States of America, responded to this appeal with silence. Germany and its allies, more exhausted by the war than England and France, entered into peace negotiations with the Soviet government. Germany wanted to retain some of the lands conquered from Russia. The arrogant German generals were forced to negotiate with delegates of workers and peasants from the Land of Soviets. The Germans presented the Soviet delegation with extortionate peace terms.
      Since the old army had collapsed, and a new regular Red Army had not yet been created and could not be created on such short notice, the Soviets could no longer continue the war. Therefore, <person >Lenin</person> obliged Trotsky, who was part of the delegation, to sign a peace treaty with the Germans. But Trotsky, clearly playing into the Germans' hands and provoking them to launch a new offensive against the unarmed Soviet Union, disrupted the peace negotiations. The Germans took advantage of this, launched a new offensive, and occupied part of Soviet territory. German troops were approaching <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>. At <person >Lenin</person>'s insistence, peace with the Germans was hastily concluded in the city of Brest. This was the Brest Peace Treaty.
      In addition to the loss of Soviet territory occupied by the Germans, they were forced to agree to other concessions to Germany. The traitor Trotsky and his henchman Bukharin did everything they could to disrupt the Brest Peace Treaty and betray the young Soviet Republic.
     
      The Red Army, in the early days of its organization.
     
      <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin, agreeing to an unfavorable peace, had no doubt that the time would come when the revolution would triumph in Germany, and Soviet power in Russia would have time to create the Red Army, grow stronger, and be able to restore what had been lost. With the conclusion of the Brest-Litovsk Peace, the Soviet government gained a respite and began to build the national economy and create and strengthen the Red Army. The Red Army was created in 1918.
      The Germans seized Soviet lands. Although the Brest-Litovsk Peace, concluded by the Soviet government with the Germans, extended to the entire territory of the Soviet state, including Ukraine, some Ukrainian delegates, bribed by the Germans, refused to submit to the Soviet government and concluded their own separate peace treaty with the Germans. By virtue of this treacherous treaty, Ukraine was declared not a Soviet republic, but a bourgeois republic. If the Soviets resisted, the Germans pledged to support the Ukrainian bourgeois government, then known as the Ukrainian Rada, with their troops. The German invaders took advantage of this treaty and entered Ukraine with their troops. They captured Ukraine, then the Don and Georgia. The advancing German army dispersed the Soviets along the way, hanging <people>Bolsheviks</people> and workers and peasants who supported Soviet power.
      The Red Army was still very weak at the time, but it did not cede Soviet lands to the Germans without a fight. At the head of the workers' detachments of Donetsk miners, poor rural peasants, and revolutionary sailors stood a favorite of the workers, a Lugansk mechanic, a selflessly brave Bolshevik, and one of the best disciples of <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin—Kliment Yefremovich Voroshilov.
      For a month and a half, Voroshilov's troops fought off the advancing Germans and White Cossack detachments on the Don. On the Don, the Cossacks blew up a bridge. Under a hail of bullets and shells from the White Cossacks, the Red Army soldiers built a bridge across the Don. Some worked, others fought the Cossacks. Voroshilov encouraged the soldiers, instilled confidence in his troops with his example of personal bravery, and managed to get the Red Army across the Don to Tsaritsyn (now Stalingrad).
      German and Austrian troops captured all of Ukraine. The Germans installed a major Ukrainian landowner, the tsarist general Skoropadsky, as hetman in Ukraine and returned the lands to the landowners and the factories to the capitalists.
     
      Nikolai Shchors is a hero of the Ukrainian Civil War.
     
      Labor organizations in Ukraine were banned. Bullets, gallows, and abuses at the hands of landowners, capitalists, and the German military descended upon the working class and peasants of Ukraine. The Germans confiscated livestock from peasants and emptied their barns of grain. Trains carrying Ukrainian grain, sugar, lard, meat, coal, and iron ore departed daily for Germany and Austria. The plunder and violence of the German invaders roused Ukrainian workers and peasants to struggle. Nikolai Shchors, the son of a railroad worker, became particularly famous for his courageous fight against the Germans. He fought the enemies of the Ukrainian workers and peasants as heroically as Vasily Ivanovich Chapayev, a hero of the Russian people. But the Germans did not hold out long in Ukraine. German soldiers barely fought off the rebellious Ukrainian workers and peasants. And when revolution broke out in Germany at the end of 1918, the German soldiers fled to Germany. Ukraine became Soviet again.
      The predatory Brest-Litovsk Treaty with the Germans was annulled by the Soviet government.
     
    </chap><chap>56. The Soviet Republic surrounded by intervention and counterrevolution.
     
      Factories and plants are state property. The struggle for bread. Russia, devastated by the World War, began the socialist revolution amidst the extreme decline of the entire national economy. Manufacturers and plant owners refused to submit to workers' control. They damaged and broke machines, neglected to repair them, left factories and plants without raw materials and fuel, and sometimes closed their enterprises altogether. The Soviet government waged a decisive struggle against these enemies, who were trying to strangle the revolution in this way.
     
      Workers' control was established in factories.
     
      Banks, railways, and then factories and plants were taken away from the capitalists. In 1918, capitalist enterprises became the property of the Soviet state. Workers and Soviet engineers were appointed directors of factories and plants. But due to a shortage of fuel and raw materials, many factories and plants could not be immediately put into operation.
      The country was short of grain. The kulaks, brutal enemies of the revolution, hid grain in pits, let it rot, and sold it to speculators, all to avoid feeding the Soviet state and the Red Army. The supply of grain to Russia's worker centers from grain-producing regions was cut off by counterrevolutionaries and interventionists who rose up against Soviet power. Famine threatened to destroy the revolution.
     
      A meeting of the Village Poor Committee in 1918.
     
      At <person >Lenin</person>'s call, workers created food detachments to collect surplus grain in the villages and fight the kulaks. At <person >Lenin</person>'s suggestion, committees of the poor (kombedy) were organized in the villages. They assisted the food detachments in taking grain from the kulaks and gave the poor horses and cattle confiscated from the kulaks.
      The Party and the Poor Peasants' Committees also attracted the middle peasantry to an alliance and friendship with the working class and the poor. The middle peasants, seeing that the Soviet government, which had given them land, was protecting them from the landlords and defeating their enemies, began to fight for the Soviets together with the working class and the poor.
      The United States, England, France, and Japan began military intervention in the Land of Soviets. The foreign bourgeoisie feared that the sparks of revolutionary fire in Russia would ignite revolutions throughout the world. Foreign capitalists also could not accept the fact that they were losing the opportunity to receive enormous income from Russia on their capital invested in Russia before the revolution. In alliance with Russian landlords and the bourgeoisie, the governments of England, France, and Japan launched a civil war against the Soviet government. In the spring of 1918, Czechoslovaks, captured by the Russians during the World War, with the support of France, launched a counterrevolutionary uprising against Soviet Russia. The Socialist Revolutionaries and <people>Mensheviks</people>, together with the Czechoslovaks, seized part of the Volga region, the Urals, and Siberia. In the summer of 1918, the British landed troops in Arkhangelsk on the White Sea and helped the White Guards overthrow Soviet power. The Japanese landed troops in Vladivostok.
      All these bourgeois states that had begun the war against Soviet power were then called the Entente, meaning alliance or allies.
      The Entente stirred up uprisings in various cities of Soviet Russia with the help of the Cadets, <people>Mensheviks</people>, and Socialist Revolutionaries. The bourgeoisie bribed bandits to assassinate the leaders of the revolution. The Bolshevik Uritsky and the Bolshevik Voldarsky, a favorite orator of the <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> workers, were killed. In the fall of 1918, after a rally at a <place = type "city">Moscow</place> factory, the Socialist Revolutionaries attempted to assassinate V. I. <person >Lenin</person>. The Socialist Revolutionaries, together with the Bukharinites and Trotskyists, were plotting an uprising. <person >Lenin</person>, bleeding profusely, was taken home. For many days, Vladimir Ilyich struggled with death. All workers followed the progress of their beloved leader's illness. A sigh of relief and joy escaped them when the recovered Ilyich returned to governing the state.
      By this time, the Entente powers had seized the White Sea coast, the Urals, and Siberia. White Cossacks attempted to capture Tsaritsyn, a major city on the Volga, and cut off grain supplies to the center of the country. The Bolshevik Central Committee sent Comrade Stalin to defend Tsaritsyn. Here, Stalin met with Voroshilov, who had arrived with Red troops from Donbass. Day and night, without rest, Stalin worked to strengthen the Tsaritsyn front. He rooted out traitors who had infiltrated the Red Army's rear, ensured the armament and supply of the troops, and sent grain down the Volga to the workers of <place = type "city">Moscow</place>, <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>, and other cities. The White Cossacks attempted to take Tsaritsyn several times, but to no avail. Stalin and Voroshilov dealt the Cossacks blow after blow and defended this important city on the Volga.
      Along with Tsaritsyn, Astrakhan, where Comrade Kirov led the Red Army, also fought the Whites. The Whites never managed to capture Astrakhan.
      Civil war in Transcaucasia and Central Asia. Germany helped the <people>Mensheviks</people>, enemies of the Georgian people, gain a foothold in Georgia. The Georgian <people>Mensheviks</people> came to power through bloodshed. They executed many workers and peasants fighting for Soviet power.
      Armenian workers and peasants also failed to immediately free themselves from bourgeois oppression. In Armenia, the Entente supported the enemies of the Armenian people, the Dashnaks.
     
      The execution of 26 Baku Bolshevik commissars in 1918.
     
      The Turks intended to seize Baku in Azerbaijan, with its large oil industry. In 1918, Soviet power reigned in Baku. The Baku Soviet was led by the Bolshevik Stepan Shaumyan and other old <people>Bolsheviks</people>—friends and disciples of Comrade Stalin. Baku nationalists, ostensibly to save the city from the Turks, invited British troops to Baku in the summer of 1918. Having occupied the city, the British arrested Shaumyan, Azizbekov, Japaridze, and other Baku commissars—26 in all—taken them to Turkmenistan, and executed them there.
      In Turkmenistan, the British destroyed Soviet power and installed a wholly obedient government of White Guards—the Socialist Revolutionaries and <people>Mensheviks</people>.
      In Khiva and Bukhara, the British helped the enemies of the Uzbek people—the Khan of Khiva and the Emir of Bukharan—retain power.
     
    </chap><chap>57. Revolution in Western Europe
     
      . The November Revolution in Germany. The Great Proletarian Revolution in Russia divided the world into two camps. On one-sixth of the globe, in Russia, the power of the proletariat—the builder of socialism—was strengthened.
      Soviet Russia, like a beacon, illuminated the path to the victory of socialism for workers in capitalist countries. The first Western European workers to rise up were the German proletarians. Germany's defeat in the World War accelerated open mass rebellion. In November 1918, an uprising broke out in German cities, in workers' centers, and in the army and navy on ships. The uprising soon spread to Austria.
      Workers overthrew the emperors of Germany and Austria-Hungary. Along with their generals and confidants, they fled the people's wrath to other countries. Republics were declared in Germany and Austria.
      Soviets began to form in Germany, but they were overwhelmingly composed of traitors to the revolution—German <people>Mensheviks</people> and Social Democrats.
      The bourgeoisie and its loyal servants, the Social Democrats, formed armed units to fight the workers. These units crushed the workers' uprisings fighting for the transfer of all power to the Soviets. The workers' uprising in the German capital, Berlin, which began in early 1919, was suppressed by the White Guards. Masses of workers died in revolutionary battles, and thousands of the revolution's best fighters were imprisoned.
      German workers' leaders Karl Liebknecht and Rosa Luxemburg were arrested and killed.
      The proletarian uprising was crushed. The bourgeoisie and its allies, the Social Democrats, came to power. A few years later, the bourgeoisie ousted the Social Democrats from the government.
      Soviet republics in Bavaria and Hungary. In only one part of Germany, Bavaria, in 1919 did the workers defeat the bourgeoisie and establish their own government—the Soviet Republic.
      The German bourgeoisie mobilized White Guard gangs, spies, and traitors to the revolution against the Bavarian workers' government. For two weeks, Bavarian workers heroically repelled enemy attacks, but their forces were weak. The workers were defeated.
      At the same time, a proletarian revolution began in Germany's neighbor, Hungary. In March 1919, Soviet power emerged victorious in Hungary. A workers' government took over the Soviet Republic. The Hungarian Red Army was created. Factories, plants, mines, banks, and railroads were declared the property of a workers' state. Working families moved from dark and damp basements into bright and spacious houses confiscated from the rich. <person >Lenin</person>, Stalin, and the entire Soviet people warmly welcomed the Hungarian Soviet Republic. But troops from neighboring bourgeois countries advanced on tiny Soviet Hungary from all sides. Soviet Hungary was strangled by them.
      The Communist International. The revolution in Germany and Hungary failed because there was no revolutionary Bolshevik party in these countries at the time. The workers followed the traitors—the leaders of the Second International. Even before the World War, <person >Lenin</person> fought against these traitors. During the World War, <person >Lenin</person> led the struggle to create a new, Third International, the Communist International.
      During the revolution in the West, during the workers' strikes and peasant movements that intensified after the World War, communist parties emerged in a number of European countries. On
      March 2, 1919, representatives of communist parties from all over the world, from various countries—Germany, England, France, Poland, Switzerland, Iran, Norway, the USA, China, and Korea—risked their lives, hiding from spies, and made their way to <place = type "city">Moscow</place> for the first congress.
      At this congress, the Third Communist International (Comintern) was founded, the leader of the working class throughout the world.
     
    </chap><chap>58. The defeat of Kolchak, Denikin, and Yudenich
     
      . Kolchak was a protege of the Entente. The Entente bourgeoisie decided to destroy the Soviets in Russia. It sent its troops to northern Russia, Siberia, Central Asia, the Caucasus, and Ukraine. The Entente organized armies and campaigns of counterrevolutionary Russian generals against <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      In Siberia in 1918, the Entente declared Tsarist Admiral Kolchak the supreme ruler of Russia. They supplied Kolchak with cannons, shells, rifles, and uniforms for his soldiers.
      Kolchak created a White Army. He mercilessly executed workers and flogged and killed peasants. Throughout Siberia, he restored tsarist order.
      Tsarist officers, landowners, capitalists, and priests flocked to Kolchak from all corners of Russia, seeing him as the best defender of their interests.
      Kolchak soon launched an offensive against Soviet Russia. He succeeded in capturing the city of Perm.
      To defeat Kolchak, the Bolshevik Party mobilized and threw its best forces to the front. In the Urals, the <people>Bolsheviks</people> strengthened the front and halted the advance of the White armies.
      In the spring of 1919, Kolchak, on orders from the Entente, launched a campaign against Soviet Russia. A terrible threat to Soviet power loomed from the east. General Denikin was advancing from the south to Kolchak's aid, while General Yudenich was advancing on <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> from the west. The Soviet people were now threatened by enemies on all sides. They were supplied by foreign capitalists.
      But the main enemy at this time was Kolchak. The main forces of the Red Army were sent there. Red Army soldiers fought selflessly against Kolchak's army. Red commanders and Bolshevik political commissars, together with the soldiers, went on the offensive in difficult times and were the first to attack Kolchak's forces, inspiring the Red Army soldiers with their courage, bravery, and fearlessness.
     
      Vasily Ivanovich Chapayev was a hero of the Civil War.
     
      M.V. Frunze commanded the Red Army forces here. Under his leadership, the Red Army defeated Kolchak in the Volga region and the Urals in 1919. Vasily Ivanovich Chapayev, a national hero, emerged in Frunze's army. The Whites feared Chapayev's division like the plague. Kolchak repeatedly sent troops against Chapaev that were many times superior to his own, yet Chapaev always emerged victorious from battles with the Whites. Once surrounded by the White Army, Chapaev and his staff perished.
      But despite some losses, the Red Army finally defeated Kolchak in the fall of 1919 and drove the remnants of his army beyond the Urals, into Siberia.
     
      Siberian partisans with homemade guns attacked Kolchak's units.
     
      At this time, workers and peasants in Siberia rebelled against Kolchak and formed partisan detachments everywhere.
      In December 1919, the workers of Irkutsk revolted and captured Kolchak and his ministers. The Revolutionary Committee executed Kolchak.
      The Red Army celebrated victory in Siberia.
      The foreign invaders were forced to flee from Western and Eastern Siberia. The Red Army, with the help of Siberian partisans—Russian workers and peasants, Buryat-Mongols, Yakuts, Evenks, Altai peoples, and other peoples of Siberia—expelled them from our country.
      Denikin and Yudenich were Entente stooges. Kolchak's defeat did not stop the Entente's struggle against the Soviet Republic. Foreign powers organized a new campaign against the Soviet Union. General Denikin achieved success in the south, capturing several regions of the Don and Ukraine. The Entente provided him with military assistance, as it had to Kolchak. Denikin assembled a large army from the mobilized population and White Cossacks and, under the command of counterrevolutionary officers, marched it on <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      The Soviet government concentrated all its forces against Denikin. <person >Lenin</person> addressed a letter to all party organizations, calling on them: "Everyone to fight Denikin!" The Bolshevik Party sent its finest to the Southern Front. Many thousands of workers and peasants joined the party and went to the front. Many Komsomol organizations went to the front en masse. Notices could be seen on the doors of several Komsomol committees: "The committee is closed; everyone has gone to the front." By the autumn of 1919, the Red Army numbered up to two and a half million workers and peasants in its ranks.
      The Central Committee of the Party instructed Comrade Stalin to organize the defeat of Denikin. Stalin quickly became aware of the dire situation at the front and developed a plan to defeat Denikin's White Guards.
      By this time, Denikin had already occupied all of Ukraine and was approaching the heart of the revolution—<place = type "city">Moscow</place>. This was the most dangerous time for the revolution. By seizing Soviet territory, Denikin everywhere restored the power of landowners and capitalists. He transferred land to landowners, factories and plants to industrialists, exacted heavy taxes from the population, and executed communists and workers and peasants fighting for Soviet power. Denikin's officers burned villages and carried out pogroms against Jews.
      The Red Army's task was to defeat the advancing White Guards. S. M. Budyonny's Cavalry Corps attacked Denikin's regiments in October 1919. Budyonny swooped down on Voronezh with his invincible cavalry, decisively routing the White cavalry there.
      Following the cavalry, the Red Army's shock regiments advanced against the Whites from Orel. Comrade Ordzhonikidze commanded military operations here. Denikin's White Army succumbed to the crushing onslaught of the Soviet troops and rolled south.
      In the winter snowstorm and icy conditions, Budyonny's Red Army regiments and cavalry continued, almost relentlessly, to drive the Whites further and further, toward the Black Sea. Denikin's forces retreated in panic, and partisan uprisings arose in their rear. These rebellions were particularly widespread in the Northern Caucasus. Under the leadership of Comrade Kirov and other <people>Bolsheviks</people>, workers and peasants from the mountain peoples launched raids against Denikin's forces. The rebels captured towns from the Whites, killing landowners and officers. Larger detachments waged actual battles against the White troops.
      Simultaneously with Denikin, the Entente sent General Yudenich's army to <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> to support him. Yudenich approached <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> in October 1919.
      The workers of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> formed a steel wall to defend the first city of the revolution. Day and night, workers and their families dug trenches and erected barbed wire entanglements. <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place> was transformed into an impregnable fortress. Tens of thousands of workers and Komsomol members joined the ranks of <place element = "city" > Petrograd </place>'s defenders. They launched an offensive and dealt Yudenich a fatal blow at the end of 1919. The remnants of his army were driven back into Estonia.
      This time, the Entente's campaign again ended in the complete defeat of the White generals. Denikin and Yudenich fled abroad. The Entente hastily withdrew its troops from the Soviet Union. The Red Army drove them from Arkhangelsk and Murmansk. The peoples of Ukraine and the North Caucasus were becoming free from the oppression of landowners and capitalists, tsarist generals and foreign invaders. The Red Army helped them become full citizens of the Soviet Union.
      Only in Crimea did General Wrangel and the remnants of Denikin's troops still remain. And to the west, Poland, under orders from the Entente, was gathering strength for a new campaign against Soviet Russia.
     
    </chap><chap>59. War with the Polish lords. The defeat of Wrangel.
     
      War with White Poland. The year 1920 arrived. The Entente continued to wage war against the Soviet Republic. Now it set Poland against the Soviets.
      Poland was restored as an independent state only in late 1918. The Great Proletarian Revolution granted the Polish people the right to secede from Russia. The Polish lords in power in Poland did not appreciate this.
      As early as 1919, they seized Minsk, the capital of Belarus, and part of Ukraine.
      The Council of People's Commissars repeatedly proposed to the Poles that they cease their seizures and violence against the Belarusian and Ukrainian civilian populations and conclude peace, but the Polish gentry would hear of it. The Polish gentry dreamed of seizing Ukraine as far as the Black Sea. The Entente supplied the Poles with cannons, machine guns, and rifles. France gave them up to 135 aircraft and its best military specialists. In the spring of 1920, the Poles marched on Soviet Russia and captured Kiev. Having crossed the Dnieper, the Polish army prepared to seize left-bank Ukraine as well. The Poles hoped to link up with the remnants of Denikin's army, entrenched in Crimea under the command of Baron Wrangel—another Entente puppet.
      The Red Army was quickly pulled together from various fronts to attack the Polish invaders. Budyonny's cavalry army was sent from the Caucasus Front to the Polish Front. The dashing cavalrymen marched a thousand kilometers at a rapid pace without dismounting. Budyonny's cavalry advanced behind the Poles and struck them near Kyiv.
      The Poles fled, relentlessly pressed by Red Army units. The Red Army soon liberated Belarus and approached the capital of Poland, Warsaw. But the Red Army did not take Warsaw and was forced to retreat.
      The Poles, despite the retreat of Soviet troops, had lost so much strength in the war that they could no longer advance and offered peace to Soviet Russia. The Soviet government agreed to peace, and in the fall of 1920, the war ended. Belarus and Ukraine regained their lands previously seized by the Polish lords. However, some Ukrainians and Belarusians living in Western Ukraine and Western Belarus remained under Polish rule.
      Wrangel's defeat. One more major enemy of the Soviet state remained – Baron Wrangel. With the help of the Entente, Wrangel built strong fortifications at Perekop on the Crimean Isthmus. The party and government commissioned M.V. Frunze to defeat Wrangel. Together with Voroshilov, Frunze, following Comrade Stalin's instructions, meticulously prepared the offensive.
      Fierce fighting began. Defeated in Ukraine, Wrangel entrenched himself behind his fortifications in Crimea. On the third anniversary of the proletarian revolution, on the orders of M.V. Frunze, on the night of November 7-8, an assault on Wrangel's Perekop fortifications began. The Red Army's offensive was conducted across completely open terrain. The White Guards fired powerful cannons at the Red Army soldiers and rained bullets from machine guns. Despite this, the heroic Red Army soldiers advanced on the Whites' concrete fortifications. Under heavy fire, the Red Army soldiers broke into the enemy trenches and overthrew them. The Battle of Perekop ended in victory for the Red Army. The White Guards fled in panic. Wrangel, with the remnants of his troops, boarded ships and fled across the Black Sea to his protectors, the Entente.
      Neither the Poles nor Wrangel helped the Entente crush Soviet power in our country. The third and final campaign of the Entente failed just as the first two had.
     
      Mikhail Vasilyevich Frunze (1885–1925).
     
      Establishment of Soviet power in Central Asia and Transcaucasia. The population of Central Asia endured terrible hardships during the civil war. Foreign invaders, kulaks (beys), and mullahs organized Basmachi bandit gangs. The Basmachi robbed the population and burned villages and auls. <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin sent a large number of Red units under the command of M.V. Frunze and V.V. Kuibyshev to the aid of the workers of Central Asia. In sandy deserts and rocky mountains, the Red Army destroyed the Basmachi gangs, liberating Central Asia from the rule of its oppressors.
      In 1920, Uzbek workers rebelled against the Khan's rule in Khiva. They defeated the Khan's troops and established a people's government. Following Khiva, a rebellion also broke out in Bukhara. The workers, aided by the Red Army, overthrew the Emir's rule and established a people's government. At the same time, the Turkmen also liberated themselves from foreign invaders.
      In the spring of 1920, workers' and peasants' uprisings began in Transcaucasia, where bourgeois nationalists ruled with the support of the Entente. Red Army units led by Comrades Ordzhonikidze, Kirov, and Mikoyan came to their aid. The bourgeois government was overthrown, and the peoples of Transcaucasia—Azerbaijan, Armenia, and Georgia—joined the united family of nations of the Soviet Union.
      Now the main enemies of the workers and peasants were defeated and expelled from Soviet soil. Soviet power triumphed over foreign and Russian capitalists because the Communist Party led the workers. The Party rallied the workers and peasants to fight their enemies and was able to utilize all the country's resources to defeat them.
      Workers from Germany, England, and France provided significant assistance to the Soviet Republic in defeating the interventionists. They prevented the shipment by rail and sea of ​​weapons and equipment intended for the fight against the Soviets. They demanded an end to the struggle against the Soviet Republic and waged the struggle under the slogan: "Hands off Soviet Russia!"
      Having defeated the interventionists, the workers of the Soviet Union could now return to peaceful work on the farm, begin building socialism, and heal the grave wounds inflicted by the world and civil wars.
     
      XIV. Transition to Peaceful Work to Rebuild the Country's Economy
     
    </chap><chap>60. Rebuilding the National Economy. The Creation of the USSR:
     
      <person >Lenin</person>'s Plan for Escape from Devastation. The world war and the civil war imposed by the Entente and counterrevolutionaries had brought the country to utter ruin. Many factories and plants were idle: there was no fuel or raw materials, broken locomotives and mangled carriages littered the railroad tracks. Bridges and railroad tracks had been blown up in many places by the Whites and had to be rebuilt. Industry produced five times less goods than before the war.
      Peasant fields were poorly cultivated. Much livestock had been taken away during the Tsarist war. Many were killed during the Civil War. Agriculture yielded half as much food as in 1914. There was famine in the country.
      Private trade was prohibited during the Civil War. Peasants, accustomed to trade, expressed discontent at this time. The bourgeoisie and kulaks, taking advantage of this discontent, roused peasants in several places to revolt against Soviet rule.
      The Party and the Soviet government decided to implement a number of measures to improve the country's economy.
      Vladimir Ilyich proposed the following plan in 1921. During the Civil War, peasants donated all their surplus grain to industry, workers, and the Red Army. Workers and peasants had formed a military alliance against landowners and factory owners. Now they needed an alliance to restore the economy and build socialism. Let the peasants not give all their surplus to the state, but pay a precisely defined tax in kind. They could dispose of their remaining products as they wish. To this end, private trade must be permitted. Private industrialists and merchants should be allowed to open small businesses and conduct trade. For the time being, let private industrialists and merchants produce and trade goods. "We will quickly grow stronger and displace private capital. And the time will come when we will completely eliminate the remnants of capitalists and kulaks in our country," <person >Lenin</person> said. <person >Lenin</person>'s plan was adopted. It was called the New Economic Policy (NEP).
      To speed up economic recovery, the Communist Party, as it had during the Civil War, held subbotniks (workdays) for the first time. All workers participated. They worked for free for the benefit of their homeland.
      <person >Lenin</person>'s plan proved successful. Within three to four years, the country's economy was firmly on its feet: factories and plants began operating, and the railways improved. Agriculture also boomed. Peasants brought grain, meat, and eggs to the markets. They began sowing beets and flax, and increased cotton cultivation. Sugar refineries and textile factories began operating across the country.
      Workers and peasants now had access to grain, sugar, fabrics, and many other goods. Many state-owned and cooperative stores opened. These enterprises began to displace private traders.
      Vladimir Ilyich <person >Lenin</person>—that mountain eagle, as Stalin called him—had a far-reaching vision. He said that workers and peasants could easily overcome devastation and lead happy lives. They would have to have factories within their own economy where machines were made, and these machines would have to run on electricity. The entire country, <person >Lenin</person> said more than once, needed to be covered with a network of power plants. A plan for the country's electrification was developed. At <person >Lenin</person>'s suggestion, construction began on the first large water-powered electric power station on the Volkhov River, near <person >Lenin</person>grad. In 1926, after <person >Lenin</person>'s death, the station was completed and provided electricity to <person >Lenin</person>grad's factories and plants. This helped restore <person >Lenin</person>grad's vital industry.
      Power stations were also built in other parts of the country: in the Urals, Ukraine, and Transcaucasia.
      The end of the Japanese intervention. While the entire Soviet Union was rebuilding its economy, our rich land—the Far East—had been under Japanese control since 1918. But in 1922, the Red Army, together with Siberian partisans, ended the war here too and liberated the entire Far East from Japanese bandits and White Guards. Red soldiers won glorious victories in battles against the White and Japanese forces near Spassk and Volochayevka. Near the village of Volochayevka, the White Guards erected strong barbed wire entanglements. In winter, in the bitter cold, naked and almost barefoot, Red soldiers marched to the entanglements, tearing the wire with their bare hands, cutting it with sabers. The fortifications were taken. The Whites and Japanese fled.
     
      Sergei Lazo—a hero of the civil war in the Far East. In 1920, Comrade Lazo was burned alive in the firebox of a locomotive by Japanese invaders.
     
      In October 1922, the Red Army liberated Vladivostok.
      The Japanese yoke over the Far East was thrown off.
      But the workers of Siberia and the Far East will long remember the violence and looting perpetrated by the Japanese army. The workers and peasants will never forget how the Japanese burned Red partisans alive in the fireboxes of locomotives. Thus died the hero Sergei Lazo for the liberation of the Far East.
      The creation of the USSR. Now the entire country was cleared of White troops and invaders. It was necessary to protect the country from further armed attacks by bourgeois countries. It was necessary to revive the economy and build socialism. It was necessary to assist all the peoples of the Land of Soviets in raising their national culture. To achieve all this, it was necessary to create a unified union state. To this end, in 1922, at the suggestion of <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin, delegates from the union republics gathered in <place = type "city">Moscow</place> for the First All-Union Congress of Soviets and formed a voluntary state association of peoples, a union state called the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR).
      Initially, the USSR united several Soviet republics: the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic (RSFSR), with its capital <place = type "city">Moscow</place>; the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic (USSR), with its capital initially in Kharkov and later in Kiev; and the Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic (BSSR), with its capital Minsk. The Transcaucasian Soviet Socialist Republics—Azerbaijan, Georgia, and Armenia—formed a single union—the Transcaucasian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic (TSFSR), with its capital Tbilisi. A little later, three independent Soviet republics were established in Central Asia: Uzbekistan, with its capital in Tashkent; Turkmenistan, with its capital in Ashgabat; and Tajikistan, with its capital in Stalinabad. These republics also became part of the USSR.
     
      V. I. <person >Lenin</person> and I. V. Stalin in Gorki during V. I. <person >Lenin</person>'s illness.
     
      The peoples of the USSR began to live as a close-knit family. Many nationalities, dying out, oppressed, and illiterate under tsarism, were now revived and began to build socialism in a fraternal union of peoples. The development of national culture took rapid strides in all the republics. Many schools, universities, and libraries were opened, theaters were built, and many books began to be printed in national languages. The peoples of the USSR, previously unwritten, received their own alphabet. The culture of the peoples flourished.
     
    </chap><chap>61. <person >Lenin</person> died, but his work lives on
     
      . The Death of <person >Lenin</person>. On January 21, 1924, at the age of 54, after a long and serious illness, the great <person >Lenin</person> died in Gorki, near <place = type "city">Moscow</place>. Working people all over the world lost their leader, who prepared and carried out the proletarian revolution, saving it from countless enemies in difficult years. A man greater than anyone had done for humanity died.
      Deepest sorrow gripped millions of working people. In the bitter January frosts, lines of <place = type "city">Moscow</place> workers walked to bid farewell to the ashes of their brilliant leader. They were overcome with deep sorrow and a firm resolve to follow the path shown by <person >Lenin</person>.
     
      <place = type "city">Moscow</place> workers walk to bid farewell to the ashes of V. I. <person >Lenin</person> in the Column Hall of the House of Unions.
     
      To the sounds of a mournful march, the people buried <person >Lenin</person> at the Kremlin wall. There he lies, as if alive, in a marble mausoleum, in a glass coffin, with the Order of the Red Banner on his chest.
      And workers from all corners of our country, arriving in <place = type "city">Moscow</place>, go to the mausoleum to capture the image of the leader who led the people to a free and happy life.
     
      The Mausoleum of V. I. <person >Lenin</person> and I. V. Stalin in <place = type "city">Moscow</place> on Red Square.
     
      Stalin's Oath. On January 26, when delegates from all over the USSR gathered for the Second All-Union Congress of Soviets, Stalin, on behalf of the Bolshevik Party, took an oath before the people on behalf of the Party. He said:
      "In leaving us, Comrade <person >Lenin</person> bequeathed to us to hold high and preserve pure the great title of Party member. We swear to you, Comrade <person >Lenin</person>, that we will fulfill this commandment of yours with honor!" ...
      "In leaving us, Comrade <person >Lenin</person> bequeathed to us to guard the unity of our Party as the apple of our eye. We swear to you, Comrade <person >Lenin</person>, that we will also fulfill this commandment of yours with honor!" ...
      "Only in our country did the oppressed and downtrodden masses of working people succeed in throwing off the rule of landowners and capitalists and replacing it with the rule of workers and peasants" ...
      "This gigantic struggle was led by Comrade <person >Lenin</person> and his Party" ...
      "The name of <person >Lenin</person> has become the most beloved name of the working and exploited masses."
      "When Comrade <person >Lenin</person> left us, he bequeathed to us the duty of preserving and strengthening the dictatorship of the proletariat. We swear to you, Comrade <person >Lenin</person>, that we will spare no effort to fulfill this commandment of yours with honor!"
     
      Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin (1879–1953).
     
      “When he left us, Comrade <person >Lenin</person> bequeathed to us the task of strengthening the union of workers and peasants with all our might. We swear to you, Comrade <person >Lenin</person>, that we will fulfill this commandment of yours with honor!”…
      “Russians and Ukrainians, Bashkirs and Belarusians, Georgians and Azerbaijanis, Armenians and Dagestanis, Tatars and Kyrgyz, Uzbeks and Turkmen—all are equally interested in strengthening the dictatorship of the proletariat.”…
      “Comrade <person >Lenin</person> tirelessly spoke to us of the need for a voluntary union of the peoples of our country, of the need for their fraternal cooperation within the Union of Republics.”
      “When he left us, Comrade <person >Lenin</person> bequeathed to us the task of strengthening and expanding the Union of Republics. ” We swear to you, Comrade <person >Lenin</person>, that we will fulfill this commandment of yours with honor! ...
      "<person >Lenin</person> repeatedly pointed out to us that strengthening the Red Army and improving its condition is one of the most important tasks of our party" ...
      "Let us swear, comrades, that we will spare no effort to strengthen our Red Army, our Red Navy."
     
      XV. Five-Year Plans of Socialism and the Great Patriotic War
     
    </chap><chap>62. Socialist Industry and Collective Farms in Agriculture (Kolkhozes)
     
      Construction of Socialist Industry. The old factories and plants that were put into operation were very backward and had outdated machinery. There were few of them, and they produced very few goods needed by the country. Little pig iron was smelted. Little oil and coal were mined. Many goods were not produced at all. They had to be imported from abroad.
     
      Vyacheslav Mikhailovich Molotov.
     
      In 1925, at the 14th Party Congress, Comrade Stalin, on the Party's instructions, declared that we must transform our agricultural country into an industrial one in the shortest possible time. To do this, we must build many new factories, plants, and power plants; and refurbish all the old plants in accordance with the latest scientific and technological advances. We must build tractors, combines, automobiles, new machine tools for factories, and airplanes. We must create many well-trained workers and specialists. We must catch up with and surpass the most advanced capitalist countries, "otherwise they will crush us." This is called industrialization.
     
      Grigory Konstantinovich Ordzhonikidze (1886–1937).
     
      But this plan for building socialism in our country was opposed by traitors within the party at the time—Trotsky, Zinoviev, and Kamenev. They strove by every means to disrupt the construction of socialist industry. They claimed that it was impossible to build a socialist society in the USSR, that workers and peasants could not do without capitalists and kulaks. The foreign bourgeoisie exploited their struggle against the party to slander the Soviet Union and fight it. They bribed some of the old specialists and the remnants of the <people>Mensheviks</people> and Socialist Revolutionaries, creating counterrevolutionary groups of saboteurs to disrupt the USSR's growing industry. The saboteurs sabotaged machinery and caused cave-ins in coal and ore mines. They blew up and burned factories, plants, and power plants. The saboteurs were caught and severely punished. But the Trotskyists continued their struggle against the party and the people. The party expelled the Trotskyists from its ranks. Trotsky was expelled from the Soviet Union by the people, and he openly went into the service of the bourgeoisie.
     
      Mikhail Ivanovich Kalinin (1875–1946).
     
      To implement the tasks set for the country by Comrade Stalin, a major project was developed in 1928—the first five-year plan for socialist construction.
      The workers of the Union enthusiastically took up this great construction project, displaying examples of labor heroism. In the Soviet Union, labor became a matter of honor and glory, a matter of valor and heroism. Intense work continued day and night at construction sites.
     
      Blast furnaces of the Kuznetsk Metallurgical Plant.
     
      Socialist competition unfolded in factories, plants, and railways. Construction workers demonstrated achievements in bricklaying, timber felling for construction sites, and building factory buildings unseen anywhere in the world.
      In 1930, on the banks of the Tom River, near the city of Kuznetsk, where the Siberian Tatar khans once held land, construction began on a massive metallurgical plant named after Stalin, which was completed by the end of the first five-year plan.
      Where the Dnieper rapids once stood, on the site of the Zaporizhian Sich, the powerful Dnieper Hydroelectric Station named after <person >Lenin</person> was built.
     
      Valerian Vladimirovich Kuibyshev (1888–1935) was the architect.
     
      With the help of the Dnieper Hydroelectric Station's electricity, many regions of Ukraine flourished. The Dnieper River, dotted with rapids, became completely navigable, and many factories around the station began to draw power from it and produce goods needed by the country.
      In 1930, the Turkestan-Siberian Railway was built across the waterless steppes and sands, connecting rich and grain-rich Siberia with flourishing Central Asia.
      During the first five-year plan, especially many factories were built in the national republics. Central Asia, Transcaucasia, Ukraine, and Belarus built dozens of new factories.
      All this made it possible to build a socialist industry, that is, an industry without capitalists.
      Collective farms were built. Tractors, the steel horses of peasant agriculture, were ready. During the first five-year plan, the powerful Dzerzhinsky Tractor Plant in Stalingrad and combine factories in Saratov and Zaporozhye were built.
      All this was necessary to ensure that peasant farming was managed according to the latest scientific and technological advances.
      This made it possible to transform small individual peasant farms into collective farms. This was a difficult task. At first, peasants still clung tightly to their small holdings.
     
      Harvesting with combines on collective farm fields.
     
      The Party managed to demonstrate to the peasants, not only in words but also in deeds, the enormous benefits and advantages of large collective farms over small ones. The Soviet government sent numerous tractors, combines, and other machines to the countryside. And in 1929, a wave of middle-class peasants followed the poor peasants into the collective farms. The kulak, seeing the end of the collective farms, began to furiously resist their organization. The kulaks killed leading collective farmers, damaged collective farm machinery, and burned collective farm grain. The kulak struggle against the collective farms was supported by a tiny group of traitors to the people, led by Bukharin and Rykov. They, like the Trotskyists, opposed the Five-Year Plan.
      But the Bolshevik Party defeated these traitors and helped the peasantry crush kulak resistance and eliminate the kulaks.
      The collective farms grew, gained strength, and began to rapidly advance toward a happy, prosperous life. The peasants on the collective farms began to sow more fields and harvest more grain. There were more schools, libraries, and clubs in the villages. By 1932, more than half of the peasant households had been united into collective farms.
      Socialist agriculture emerged in the Soviet Union—that is, agriculture without landowners or kulaks.
      In 1932, the five-year plan for socialist construction was completed in four years. Workers and peasants could celebrate victory. The USSR, having fulfilled the first five-year plan, ensured the victory of socialism. The USSR now produced cars, mined metal, built tractors and aircraft, and increased coal and oil production. The USSR had become an industrial country.
      It now produced three times more food than Tsarist Russia. By 1933, the USSR had caught up with and surpassed a number of European countries. It ranked second in the world in oil production, second in steel production, third in pig iron production, and fourth in coal production.
      But enemies both within the USSR and abroad hindered the construction of factories in our country. In 1929, foreign capitalists forced China to wage war against the USSR. Troops of Chinese generals and White Guards attacked our Far Eastern borders. But the Red Army in the Far East was strong and resilient, quickly defeating the enemies. There were saboteurs within the country as well. In 1930, a large group of saboteurs, including veteran engineers, <people>Mensheviks</people>, and Socialist Revolutionaries, were rounded up. They wanted capitalists to return to our country and were preparing a new war against the USSR. The saboteurs were caught and severely punished by the Soviet government. After this, workers and peasants further strengthened and armed their Red Army and helped the Chekists expose the enemies of the Soviet people.
      Thus, through labor and battle, the first five-year plan for the great projects outlined by the Bolshevik Party was completed.
     
    </chap><chap>63. The USSR – a Socialist Country.
     
      Cultural Achievements and People of the Socialist Country. During the First Five-Year Plan, the face of our country changed dramatically. During the Second Five-Year Plan (1933–1937), an even more radical restructuring of our entire life took place. On one-sixth of the globe, from the North Pole to the scorching steppes of Turkmenistan, from the Baltic Sea to the Pacific Ocean, a new, socialist system was created; a new life was created without exploitation and oppression, without capitalists and landowners, without merchants and kulaks.
      The country began to function in a new way. The people of the Land of Soviets discovered the riches hidden in the bowels of the earth. The extraction of coal, oil, gold, platinum, iron ore, and non-ferrous metals reached previously unheard-of levels. In the rich forests of the USSR, people began to harvest a huge variety of wood species. In our oceans, seas, lakes, and rivers, people increased the harvest of marine animals and valuable fish to unprecedented levels. During the Second Five-Year Plan, socialist fields supplied the country with the necessary quantities of grain, cotton, flax, and beets. Increasing quantities of tea, tangerines, lemons, oranges, apples, pears, and grapes were grown in socialist fields and orchards.
      Dozens of giant factories, built using the latest science and technology by Soviet engineers and equipped with Soviet machinery, expanded production and improved their products year after year. Hundreds of new factories were built in industries that had never existed before. Our automobiles, tractors, combines, airplanes, and machine tools for factories and plants are in no way inferior to foreign ones.
      Only the workers and peasants of the USSR, liberated from capitalist exploitation, were able to create such a powerful industry and such a robust agriculture in such a short time. Caring for people—the shortest working hours in the world, high wages, rest homes, sanatoriums, occupational safety at work, good housing, and training in technical and other skills—created an unprecedented rise in labor productivity. Labor ceased to be a yoke.
      New, special people emerged in the Soviet Union.
      In the Donets Basin, coal miner Alexey Stakhanov mined 102 tons of coal in a single shift, more than 14 times the norm.
      At the Gorky automobile plant, blacksmith Busygin forged 1,050 crankshafts in a single shift instead of the standard 675.
      The Vinogradov weavers began working on 144 looms instead of 10. Hundreds and thousands of others followed these pioneering figures, dubbed Stakhanovites. The Stakhanovite movement swept the entire country, spreading from factories to agriculture. Collective farmers began harvesting unprecedented crops. Maria Demchenko achieved a harvest of 500 centners of beets per hectare.
     
      Alexey Stakhanov is a famous miner of the Donbass.
     
      Tractor drivers from Pasha Angelina's team plow over a thousand hectares with a single tractor each summer.
      Our country needed well-established transportation, and this task was successfully accomplished.
      Canals were dug—the White Sea-Baltic Canal, connecting the Baltic Sea with the White Sea, and the <place = type "city">Moscow</place> Canal.
      A marvelously beautiful metro system, the best in the world, was built in the capital of the USSR, <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      Soviet airplanes paved routes to the previously unknown icy wastes of the Arctic, conquered the North Pole, and established a radio station there. Soviet pilots discovered a previously unknown route across the North Pole from the USSR to America. The names of Soviet polar explorers and pilots—Heroes of the Soviet Union—Schmidt, Chkalov, Baidukov, Belyakov, Gromov, Yumashev, Danilin, Vodopyanov, Molokov, Slepnev, and others—are known throughout the country.
     
      New <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
     
      The Palace of Soviets project in <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
     
      New cities in the USSR grew with incredible speed—Stalinsk in Western Siberia, Magnitogorsk in the Urals, Komsomolsk in the Far East, and others. Old cities were rebuilt and became unrecognizable.
      The capitals of the Soviet republics and major industrial centers especially grew and became more beautiful. Old <place = type "city">Moscow</place>, with its crooked streets, was transformed into the glittering capital of the Soviet Union. Hundreds of beautiful buildings were erected in <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      16-, 26-, and 32-story buildings were built in our capital.
      The Palace of Soviets, with its sculpture of V. I. <person >Lenin</person> at its top, will be one of the most remarkable buildings in the world.
      The capitalist system was a grave for popular talent. Only a few individuals managed to break through to creative and scientific careers. Such was I. V. Michurin, a great horticulturist of our country. He cultivated many new varieties of fruit. They are frost-resistant. Michurin's apple trees blossom and bend under the weight of their fruit in the frigid Siberia and the Far North. His scientific discoveries were appreciated only by the Soviet authorities.
      Another talent—the grandfather of Russian aviation—K.E. Tsiolkovsky designed an airplane 13 years before the first plane took flight. He invented a metal airship several years before the first airship was invented in Germany. However, these inventions were not appreciated in Tsarist Russia. Only in the Soviet Union did Tsiolkovsky's work find application.
      Only under Soviet rule did Academician I.P. Pavlov widely expand his scientific work. Surrounded by the care of the Soviet people and supported by the Soviet government, I.P. Pavlov made many discoveries about human life.
      Our country raised and educated thousands of new scientists from among workers and peasants in its numerous schools and universities.
      Soviet musicians and artists are first-class masters of art. Soviet pianists and violinists have received top awards at international competitions.
      Every schoolchild can become whatever they want. All peoples of the Soviet Union were given the opportunity to study in their native languages.
      No other country in the world publishes as many books or produces as many newspapers as the USSR. Nowhere else are there as many libraries as ours.
     
      Maxim Gorky (1868–1936).
     
      Folk art in the USSR enjoyed the broadest development. Folk talents flourished in theater, literature, and film. Under the Party's leadership, these talents were nurtured and cultivated by the great proletarian writer Maxim Gorky, a personal friend of <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin. Inspired by the construction of socialism in our country, Gorky wrote fiery pages of unforgettable literary works. Together with all the people, Gorky built a happy life in our country.
     
      Sergei Mironovich Kirov (1886–1934).
     
      In 1934, at the 17th Congress of the Bolshevik Party, the great leader of the people, Stalin, said: "Everyone can see that the Party line has won." This means that the path shown by the Bolshevik Party was the right one.
      Millions of workers in the Soviet Union and abroad echoed Stalin's words: "The Party line has won."
      The remnants of the parasitic capitalist and kulak class were destroyed. They will never rise again in the Soviet Union.
      The Party fulfilled <person >Lenin</person>'s great legacy. Under its leadership, the people created a new, socialist system. The people strengthened their beloved Motherland.
      Only in a socialist country could such courageous people emerge—people who, loving their homeland, do not hesitate to lay down their lives for it.
     
      The October Parade in <place = type "city">Moscow</place> on Red Square.
     
      Semyon Mikhailovich Budyonny.
     
      But the USSR is surrounded by countries dominated by capitalists, and therefore spies and saboteurs will not cease trying to infiltrate our country and harm us.
      The eyes of the worker and peasant must be sharper.
      All residents of the Land of Soviets, from the youngest to the oldest, must guard their borders more vigilantly.
      The Soviet Army and our friends beyond the borders of the USSR. The Soviet Union is as strong and robust as any other state in the world. It is strong because of its Soviet Army, armed with the latest technology and science. It is renowned for its marshals and commanders, its heroic soldiers.
      It is even stronger because the entire people, as one, men and women, children, adults and the elderly, will defend their beloved and dear homeland to the last drop of blood.
      The Soviet Union is the socialist fatherland of workers throughout the world, a mighty bulwark of freedom and happiness for all progressive humanity. Advanced workers of all countries sympathize with the USSR and wish it success. The support of these peoples and advanced workers makes the USSR even more powerful.
     
    </chap><chap>64. The New Constitution of the USSR
     
      How our state is built. The Great Proletarian Revolution destroyed and abolished the hated tsarist monarchy and its laws that kept workers and peasants in chains.
      The liberated workers and peasants built their own state on the ruins of old Russia. It was a workers' and peasants' state unprecedented in the world, which they called the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic (RSFSR).
     
      Lazar Moiseevich Kaganovich.
     
      For three years, the Soviet Republic fought off enemies pressing in from all sides. It defeated the landowners and capitalists, Russian and foreign, who had organized a civil war against it. It helped all the oppressed peoples of old Russia throw off the yoke of landowner and capitalist violence. It helped them establish Soviet power on their liberated lands. Soviet republics emerged and were strengthened in Ukraine, Belarus, Central Asia, and Transcaucasia. Through the combined efforts of all these Soviet republics, all enemies were finally defeated. The liberated peoples began to rebuild their war-torn economies. In 1922, under the leadership of the Bolshevik Party, they created the great Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. The USSR initially included four union republics, later joined by three more.
      Nowhere in the world has there been, or continues to be, such friendship and mutual trust among peoples as in the USSR. In 1924, the free peoples of the USSR adopted the first Constitution of the USSR (the Basic Law of the State). In it, they enshrined the country's victories. Much time has passed since then—industry has been built and expanded enormously, collective and state farms have been established, culture has flourished, the remnants of landowners, capitalists, and kulaks have been uprooted and destroyed, the exploitation of workers and oppression of people have been abolished. But in our country, enemies of the Soviet people, enemies of the USSR, still remained. It was they—the friends of Trotsky, Zinoviev, and Kamenev, and with them Rykov and Bukharin—who organized a gang of murderers, saboteurs, and spies in the USSR. It was they who viciously murdered Sergei Mironovich Kirov, a Bolshevik loyal to the people. They also brought about the death of the great Russian writer Maxim Gorky. They assassinated V. V. Kuibyshev and V. R. Menzhinsky.
      Trotskyists and Rykovites did whatever they could: sabotaged machinery in factories and plants, blew up mines and railway bridges, and caused train derailments. They dreamed of destroying state farms, of destroying our powerful collective farm economy. They dreamed of handing over our rich Soviet Ukraine to the Germans and the Far East to the Japanese. They dreamed of war and the military defeat of the USSR. Soviet power mercilessly and promptly eliminated the enemies of the Soviet people. Socialism triumphed in the USSR.
     
      In 1936, a commission led by I. V. Stalin drafted a new Constitution of the USSR. It was submitted for broad public debate and then approved by the highest governing body of the Union—the All-Union Congress of Soviets. The day the Constitution was approved, December 5, was declared a national holiday. The Constitution enshrines the most important achievements of the Soviet Union during its 19 years of existence.
      The previous Constitution stated that our republic was called socialist because the working class held power and strove to build socialism. The new Constitution calls our state a socialist state of workers and peasants because socialism had already been largely built in the USSR.
      In the USSR, all power belongs to the workers of the city and village—the Soviets of Workers' Deputies.
      The land, its mineral wealth, factories, mines, plants, railways, large buildings, and state farms (state farms) are the property of the state and the common property of the people.
      Alongside state ownership, there is cooperative and collective farm ownership, the property of individual collective farms, and cooperative associations.
      The Constitution stipulates that small-scale farming by artisans and individual peasants is also permitted in the USSR, but only on the condition that such artisans or individual peasants work independently and do not exploit the labor of others.
      Our state achieved all this because it abolished the landowners and capitalists, destroyed the kulaks, and abolished the exploitation of man by man.
      In the USSR, all people capable of labor must work. "He who does not work, neither shall he eat."
      The USSR is a voluntary and friendly association of equal peoples. "And this friendship is a great thing: as long as it exists," said Stalin, "the peoples of our country will be free and invincible."
      Currently, the USSR is a voluntary association of 16 equal union republics. The USSR includes:
      the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic,
      the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Byelorussian Soviet Socialist
      Republic, the Uzbek Soviet Socialist
      Republic, the Kazakh Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Georgian Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Azerbaijan Soviet
      Socialist Republic, the Lithuanian Soviet
      Socialist Republic, the Moldavian Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Latvian Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Kirghiz Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Tajik
      Soviet Socialist Republic, the Armenian Soviet Socialist Republic,
      the Turkmen Soviet Socialist Republic, the
      Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic, and
      the Karelo-Finnish Soviet Socialist Republic.
     
      The highest body of state power in the USSR is the Supreme Soviet of the USSR. Only the Supreme Soviet has the right to issue laws. It forms the government of the USSR — the Council of Ministers of the USSR.
      At the local level, the organs of power everywhere are the councils of workers' deputies. All local councils, as well as the supreme councils of the union and autonomous republics, as well as the Supreme Soviet of the USSR, are elected by citizens of the USSR on the basis of universal, equal, and direct suffrage by secret ballot. All citizens of the USSR, both men and women, who have reached the age of 18, regardless of race, nationality, religion, educational qualifications, social origin, property status, or past activities, have the right to participate in the elections of deputies, with the exception of the insane and individuals convicted by a court with deprivation of voting rights. Citizens who have reached the age of 23 may be elected to the Supreme Soviet of the USSR. Such elections are called universal. All citizens have equal rights in elections. Citizens of our country elect deputies to all bodies of government by personal vote. Such elections are called direct elections.
      Voting in elections is secret; every citizen votes for the person they wish to elect to the council.
      Citizens of the USSR have the right to work, rest, education, and financial security in old age. These rights are guaranteed by our state. In a socialist country, there is no unemployment, which affects millions of workers in capitalist countries.
      Thousands of rest homes and sanatoriums are open to workers. Every year, all workers and employees of the USSR are granted vacation.
      In the USSR, all workers can study and receive an education. The state provides scholarships to many students.
      In the USSR, every person is cared for from birth to old age. Nurseries and kindergartens are organized for children. The elderly and sick are provided with state assistance. All citizens of the USSR are guaranteed freedom of speech, press, assembly, and street demonstrations.
      But in addition to rights, every citizen of the USSR also has responsibilities to the state. All citizens are obliged to strictly comply with the laws of the Soviet Union, maintain discipline, work honestly, and protect and strengthen socialist property. Anyone who encroaches on socialist property is an enemy of the peoples of the USSR.
      Defending the Fatherland from any and all enemies of the USSR is the highest duty of a citizen of the USSR. If anyone goes over to the enemy's side or reveals the USSR's military secrets to the enemy, he will betray his homeland, his people, and will be punished as an enemy of the USSR.
     
    </chap><chap>65. New Soviet Republics
     
      The reunification of Western Ukraine with the Ukrainian SSR and Western Belarus with the Byelorussian SSR. The USSR was building a peaceful life. Meanwhile, a new world war was being prepared in Western Europe. The fascists had seized power in Germany. They were the worst enemies of the working people. The leader of the fascists, Hitler, wanted to subjugate the entire world. He said that all peoples should work for the Germans and be their slaves. Above all, he wanted to turn all Slavs into slaves: Czechoslovakians, Poles, Belarusians, Ukrainians, Russians, and others.
      In 1938, Germany started World War II. It captured Czechoslovakia and a year later attacked Poland. The reckless Polish government was unprepared for war. The Polish army was easily defeated. Poland's rulers fled, abandoning their country to the mercy of the enemy.
      The lands of Western Belarus and Western Ukraine were under Polish control. A terrible enemy was approaching. Ukrainians and Belarusians were facing disaster. Then, on September 17, 1939, Soviet troops entered Western Ukraine and Western Belarus and took their populations under their protection. The fascist bandits stopped and advanced no further.
      Ukrainians and Belarusians joyfully greeted their saviors—the Soviet soldiers. Flowers were strewn along the path of our tanks. The peoples of Western Ukraine and Western Belarus unanimously expressed their desire to join the Soviet Union and reunite with Soviet Ukraine and Soviet Belarus. Thus, the close-knit family of Soviet peoples was replenished.
      The formation of new Soviet republics. The German conquest of Poland caused alarm in neighboring states—Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia. They were threatened with Nazi enslavement. The peoples of these countries looked to the Soviet Union with hope. In 1940, they proclaimed Soviet sovereignty and declared their desire to join the USSR. Thus, three more new union republics were formed. Thus, the borders of our homeland moved to the shores of the Baltic Sea. This strengthened the Soviet Union even further.
      At the same time, our government entered into negotiations with Romania. During the Civil War, Romania had seized Soviet Bessarabia. Large Romanian landowners—the boyars—cruelly oppressed its population. The people of Bessarabia and neighboring Bukovina continued their struggle for freedom. Romanian prisons were overflowing with liberation fighters. The Soviet government demanded that Romania liberate Bessarabia and Bukovina, and the issue of these lands was peacefully resolved. Bessarabia and Bukovina became Soviet. Bessarabia united with Soviet Moldova, creating the Moldavian SSR.
      A terrible threat loomed over <person >Lenin</person>grad. This great city was located right next to the border with Finland. The fascists dominated Finland. They dreamed of capturing <person >Lenin</person>grad and other Soviet lands and started a war against us. The armed forces of the USSR broke through the impregnable Finnish fortifications and dealt the Finns a crushing blow. The border was pushed back from <person >Lenin</person>grad. Part of the liberated lands was united with Soviet Karelia to form the Karelo-Finnish SSR.
      Thus, in 1939 and 1940, the Soviet Union grew, strengthened, expanded, and fortified its western borders. The USSR stood firm, like an impregnable fortress. Comrade Stalin said: "We do not want war, but we are ready to respond blow for blow from the warmongers."
     
    </chap><chap>66. The Great Patriotic War
     
      . The enemy's attack. Meanwhile, the world war escalated. Nazi Germany captured Norway, Denmark, Holland, Belgium, Yugoslavia, and Greece. It was assisted by Italy, Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria, and Finland. France and England opposed Germany, and then the United States of America joined them. France was led by traitors. They fought the fascists in words, but in reality they aided them. The French army was betrayed, and the Germans, having easily defeated it, took control of all of France. Almost all of Europe fell under the control of Hitler.
      The Soviet Union was against the war and constantly fought for peace. Therefore, our government concluded a non-aggression pact with Germany. According to this pact, Nazi Germany could not attack us. But the Nazis did not keep their word. They concentrated a large army on our border and treacherously attacked the USSR. This was on June 22, 1941. Thousands of German tanks devastated our land, thousands of Nazi planes dropped bombs on our peaceful cities. Having broken into our country, the enemy drenched it in blood.
      The attack was sudden. Soviet people worked peacefully. It took time to mobilize them into the army. Moreover, we had fewer tanks, planes, and guns than the Germans, since the Nazis had equipment from almost all of Europe. Therefore, our units retreated in battle, while the enemy advanced and rushed towards <place = type "city">Moscow</place> and <person >Lenin</person>grad. Hitler boasted that the Soviet armed forces had been defeated and that within weeks the entire Soviet Union would be conquered.
     
      The Supreme Commander-in-Chief, Generalissimo Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin (1879–1953),
     
      was the commander-in-chief. But at the head of our homeland stood Comrade Stalin. He knew the strength of the Soviet people and was confident of our victory. Comrade Stalin inspired everyone to fight the cruel enemy. He called for a concerted effort to defeat the invaders, to defend every inch of Soviet soil, to fight to the last drop of blood. He called for increased work in the rear to provide the army with everything it needed. He called for the creation of partisan detachments in enemy-held areas, to attack and kill the fascists, to blow up bridges and roads, to derail trains, to disrupt telephone and telegraph communications, to set fire to forests, warehouses, and supply trains, and to leave nothing for the enemy.
      At Comrade Stalin's call, all Soviet peoples rose as one to fight for their homeland. Everyone understood that this was the Great Patriotic War, a war for the liberation and independence of our beloved homeland. Everyone knew: if we win, we will be free, but if we are defeated, we will become slaves to the German princes and barons.
      The workers of <place = type "city">Moscow</place> and <person >Lenin</person>grad prepared for defense. Many old men and women took up arms and joined the militia. Thousands of Muscovites and <person >Lenin</person>graders dug trenches and anti-tank ditches, built fortifications, and extinguished fires ignited by enemy bombs.
      The Soviet Army displayed miracles of heroism near <place = type "city">Moscow</place> and <person >Lenin</person>grad. For example, on the approaches to <place = type "city">Moscow</place>, 28 guardsmen from General Panfilov's division withstood an onslaught of 50 German tanks. They cried, "There is nowhere further to retreat. <place = type "city">Moscow</place> is behind us." They knew they would perish in an unequal battle, but they didn't waver, fighting to their last breath and holding off the tanks for four hours, destroying 14 of them. The entire nation fought with such courage.
      By the beginning of winter 1941, the enemy had not only been held back but also driven back from <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      The Germans still had plenty of strength. Having suffered defeats near <place = type "city">Moscow</place> and <person >Lenin</person>grad, they launched an offensive in the south in the summer of 1942. The Nazis were pushing east. Devastating Soviet lands, they invaded the fertile steppes of the Northern Caucasus, approached the Volga near Stalingrad, and stopped on the Don near Voronezh.
      The Germans wanted to outflank <place = type "city">Moscow</place> and cut it off from the Urals and Siberia. The danger was great. Our homeland strained every nerve to fight.
      In areas captured by the enemy. Capturing Soviet lands, the Nazis devastated them. They stole grain, livestock, and various foodstuffs from the population. They destroyed libraries, schools, and museums. They took everything of value for themselves and took it to Germany. Soviet people were forced to work for the Germans. Thousands of men, women, and girls were deported to Germany and sold into slavery to German landowners and kulaks.
      The Nazis tortured and executed people for the slightest resistance. Gallows were erected in town and village squares.
      But no amount of persecution could intimidate the Soviet people. To fight the invaders, partisan detachments were formed everywhere. The partisans carried out Comrade Stalin's orders: they attacked Nazi garrisons, blew up bridges, and derailed trains. When captured by the enemy, the partisans steadfastly endured excruciating torture, never revealing anything the enemy wanted to know. Thus, Soviet girls died heroically—Zoya Kosmodemyanskaya, Liza Chaikina, pioneer Sasha Chekalin, and many others. But hundreds of thousands of Nazis were killed by the partisans
      in the Soviet rear. At the same time, our homeland had become a single military camp. Men went to the front. Women and the elderly replaced those who had left in the rear. Collective farmers provided the country with bread, food, and raw materials for industry. Workers worked day and night. Many new factories were built. The country produced more and more tanks, planes, guns, mortars, and shells. Trains ran continuously along the railways to the west, delivering everything necessary to the front. Our tanks, planes, and guns proved superior to the Germans. And soon, we outstripped the Nazis in terms of weaponry.
      Heroes of the front. Soviet people selflessly and heroically fought against the enemy.
      Captain Gastello's plane caught fire in battle. The pilot could have parachuted, but he didn't. Gastello flew the flaming plane into a column of enemy gasoline vehicles and blew them up.
      Brave Russian pilots Zdorovtsev and Kharitonov expended all their ammunition in aerial combat. But they didn't want to lose the enemy and aimed their planes at their bombers. The German planes were rammed, and our heroic pilots remained unharmed.
      Soldier Matrosov was advancing with his unit. A machine gun was firing from a Nazi fortification. Matrosov rushed to it and shielded it with his body. The machine gun failed to fire, and our forces broke through the enemy defenses.
      Azerbaijani Gusein Aliyev single-handedly engaged several Nazi aircraft. Seventeen wounds covered his body, but he shot down the enemy and emerged victorious.
      A brave fighter from Kazakhstan, Torupsabayev, was advancing on the attack. A German gunshot struck his platoon commander. Confusion ensued. Then Torupsabayev ran forward and shouted, "For the Motherland!" He led his platoon against the Germans. The enemy wavered, and when the battle ended, Torupsabayev simply said, "My job is small—to defeat the Germans. But together, we are a great force."
      Thus, the workers and peasants, all the peoples of the Soviet Union, rose up in unison, both at the rear and at the front, to fight the hated enemy.
      The Nazi invaders were routed. In the autumn of 1942, the Germans were held back near Stalingrad. Every day, they rained thousands of bombs on the city, pounding it with heavy artillery. The city was reduced to rubble, but it did not surrender. Here, Comrade Stalin prepared a crushing blow for the enemy.
      In November, the Soviet Army launched an offensive at Stalingrad. At the appointed hour, Soviet artillery thundered, tanks advanced, and infantry charged. The great Battle of Stalingrad had begun. The German front was broken. 300,000 fascist soldiers were encircled and routed. The invaders were driven from the Volga, Don, and the North Caucasus. Thus began the liberation of our lands.
      It was not easy to drive back the brutal enemy. He fought back furiously, but was routed in a series of major battles: at Kursk, <person >Lenin</person>grad, on the Dnieper, in Crimea, in Belarus, in Bessarabia, and in the Baltics. In all these battles, many German divisions were destroyed or disabled.
      Withdrawing from Soviet soil, the vicious enemy sought to destroy everything. As they retreated, the Nazis burned villages and towns. They killed thousands of Soviet people—even children were spared. They took everything of value with them.
      In the summer of 1944, all Soviet soil was cleared of the invaders. Victory salutes thundered joyfully in <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      The unity of freedom-loving peoples. The Soviet Army extended military operations beyond our homeland's borders and soon decisively defeated Germany's allies—Romania, Bulgaria, Finland, and Hungary. Our troops entered their lands. All these states admitted defeat. Their peoples expelled their rulers and, together with the Soviet Army, began the war against Nazi Germany. Dealing blow after blow to the Germans, our army liberated Poland, Yugoslavia, and Czechoslovakia. The peoples enslaved by the Nazis greeted their liberator with gratitude. They saw and understood that the Soviet Union was their best friend.
      The friendship between all freedom-loving peoples grew stronger with each passing day.
      The Soviet Union bore the brunt of the war.
      For three years of war, England and the United States of America delayed opening a second front in Europe against German troops by every means possible. But when, after the Soviet Army's enormous victories, it became clear that the Soviet Union alone could completely defeat the enemy, occupy German territory, and liberate all of Western Europe, including France, England and the United States opened a second front in Europe. In June 1944, British and American troops crossed the sea from England and landed on the coast of northern France.
      Victory over Nazi Germany. In January 1945, the Soviet Army entered Germany. Generalissimo of the Soviet Union Comrade Stalin called for "pursuing the wounded German beast on the heels and finishing it off in its own lair." German fortifications were breached, fortresses destroyed.
      Soviet troops surrounded large groups of German troops and, if they did not surrender, they were destroyed. The valiant Soviet troops advanced rapidly, crushing the enemy on its own territory. Our victorious banners fluttered over enemy territory.
      By April 21, 1945, our soldiers had already reached Berlin and engaged in battle on its outskirts. A few days later, Berlin was surrounded on all sides, and on May 2, it was captured by troops of the 1st Ukrainian and 1st Belorussian Fronts. The capture of the German capital was the most powerful blow to Germany, followed by its defeat. On May 8, Nazi Germany capitulated (surrendered to the mercy of the victor). The entire Soviet Union, as well as other countries that had fought against Germany, celebrated the victory over the fascist beast.
      The Soviet government declared May 9 Victory Day, a day of national celebration for the Soviet people.
      Thus, Hitler's wild ideas to enslave the Slavic peoples were not destined to come true. The centuries-long struggle of the Slavic peoples for their existence and independence ended in victory over the German invaders.
     
      Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev, First Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union.
     
      The defeat of Japan. Japan was Germany's ally in the Far East. The Japanese invaders sought to enslave China and other countries. They also repeatedly attacked our homeland.
      To ensure our country's security not only in the West but also in the East, to shorten the end of the war, and to facilitate the speedy restoration of world peace, the Soviet Union entered the war against the Japanese invaders. On September 2, 1945, under the crushing blows of the Soviet Army, Japan admitted defeat and laid down its arms.
     
      Kliment Yefremovich Voroshilov, Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR.
     
      The exploits of the Soviet people, and above all the Russian people, the most outstanding of all the nations comprising the Soviet Union, won victory for our country. Thanks to the heroic efforts of the front and rear, the Soviet people, led by their great commander, Comrade Stalin, managed to defeat the enemy and save the homeland from enslavement.
     
    </chap><chap>67. USSR after the war.
     
      As a result of the Great Patriotic War, our homeland grew even stronger, its influence and authority increased among all countries of the world.
      In October 1952, the 19th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union convened in <place = type "city">Moscow</place>. The congress adopted a new five-year plan for 1951–1955.
      This plan outlined a new, powerful upsurge in the country's entire national economy.
      On March 5, 1953, the Soviet people and workers around the world suffered a grave, irreparable loss. Stalin, <person >Lenin</person>'s disciple and successor, died at the age of 73.
      The death of I. V. Stalin, who dedicated his entire life to serving the people, was a profound loss. The bright memory of I. V. Stalin will live forever in the hearts of working people throughout the world.
      After the death of I. V. Stalin, our people rallied even more closely around the Communist Party and the Soviet government.
      All the efforts of the Soviet people are focused primarily on the development of heavy industry. In our country, the production of metal, machinery, and electricity increases every year, while coal and oil production grows.
      The growth of heavy industry helps develop agriculture, light industry, and the food industry, strengthening our country's defense.
      The Communist Party and the Soviet government are constantly committed to improving the lives of our people.
     
      Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the USSR Nikolai Alexandrovich Bulganin.
     
      The party and government are led by loyal and proven disciples and comrades of <person >Lenin</person> and Stalin. Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev was elected First Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, Kliment Yefremovich Voroshilov was elected Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR, and Nikolai Alexandrovich Bulganin was appointed Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the USSR.
      Under the leadership of the Communist Party and the Soviet government, the workers of our country are confidently moving towards the bright goal of communism.
     
      Chronological table
     
      911 Oleg's treaty with the Greeks.
      988 Introduction of Christianity to Russia.
      1147 First mention of <place = type "city">Moscow</place> in the annals.
      1240 Batu's conquest of the Russian principalities.
      1242 Victory of Alexander Nevsky over the German knights ("Beat the Ice").
      1328-1341 Ivan Kalita, first Grand Duke of <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      1380 Battle of Kulikovo.
      1462–1505 Ivan III, Grand Prince of <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      1480 Liberation of the Russian state from the Tatar-Mongol yoke under Ivan III.
      1547 Ivan IV assumes the title of tsar.
      1581 Yermak's campaign in Western Siberia.
      1606–1607 Uprising of peasants and Cossacks led by Bolotnikov.
      1612 Expulsion of the Poles from <place = type "city">Moscow</place>.
      1648 Uprising of Cossacks and peasants: in Ukraine under the leadership of Bohdan Khmelnytsky against the oppression of the gentry.
      1649 Final enslavement of the peasants.
      1651 Reunification of Ukraine with Russia.
      1670–1671 Peasant uprising led by Razin.
      1682–1725 Reign of Peter I.
      1703 Foundation of St. Petersburg (now <person >Lenin</person>grad).
      1707 Uprising of Cossacks and peasants led by Bulavin.
      1709 Defeat of the Swedes at Poltava by Peter I.
      1721 Peter I assumes the title of Russian Emperor.
      1773–1775 Uprising of peasants, Cossacks, and peoples of the Volga and Ural regions led by Pugachev.
      1789 Beginning of the French bourgeois revolution.
      1801 Annexation of Georgia to Russia.
      1812 Russia's war with Napoleon I.
      1818–1883 ​​The life of the brilliant leader of the proletariat Karl Marx.
      1820–1893 The life of the brilliant leader of the proletariat Friedrich Engels.
      1825 Decembrist Uprising.
      1848 Bourgeois revolutions in France, Germany, and Austria-Hungary.
      1853–1856 Crimean War.
      1861 Peasant reform.
      1864 Founding of the First International by Marx and Engels.
      1870–1924 Life of the brilliant leader of the proletariat Vladimir Ilyich <person >Lenin</person>.
      1871 Paris Commune.
      1879–1953 Life of the brilliant leader of the proletariat Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin.
      1885 Workers' strike at the Morozov factory in Orekhovo-Zuyevo.
      1903 Creation of the Russian Social Democratic Labor Party.
      1905–1907 The first bourgeois revolution in Russia.
      1912 Execution of workers in the Lena goldfields.
      1912 Formation of the Russian Social Democratic Labor Party-<people>Bolsheviks</people>.
      1914–1918 World imperialist war.
      1917 February. The second bourgeois revolution in Russia.
      1917 October. The Great October Socialist Revolution in Russia.
      1917. Creation of the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic.
      1918. Organization of the Red Army.
      1918. Defeat of the German interventionists in Ukraine.
      1918. Revolution in Germany and Austria-Hungary.
      1919 Foundation of the Communist International.
      1919 Defeat of Kolchak, Denikin, Yudenich.
      1920 War with the Polish lords and defeat of Wrangel.
      1922 Defeat of the Japanese interventionists in the Far East.
      1922 Creation of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.
      1928–1932 First Five-Year Plan.
      1933–1937 Second Five-Year Plan.
      1934 The villainous murder of S. M. Kirov by enemies of the people — Trotskyists.
      1936 December 5. Approval of the new Constitution of the USSR.
      1939 Liberation of Western Ukraine and Western Belarus by Soviet troops.
      1940 Signing of a peace treaty between the USSR and Finland. Transformation of the Karelian Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic into the Union Karelo-Finnish Soviet Socialist Republic.
      1940 Liberation of Bessarabia and Northern Bukovina from the yoke of the Romanian boyars. Formation of the Union Moldavian Soviet Socialist Republic.
      1940 Admission of the Lithuanian, Latvian and Estonian Soviet Socialist Republics to the USSR.
      1941 June 22. Perfidious attack of Nazi Germany on the USSR.
      1945 May 2. Capture of Berlin by Soviet troops.
      1945 Capitulation of Nazi Germany.
      1945 Capitulation of Japan.
      1952 Nineteenth Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union.
      1951–1955 Fifth Five-Year Plan.
    </chap></start>
 

 

HomeTexts of BK booksBK AudiobooksPolit-infoSoviet textbooksBeyond the pages of the textbookPhoto-PeterTechnical bookRadio playsChildren's library


☭ Boris Karlov 2001-3001 ☭
</chap_52_67>
</textbook>
